Thiago da Mata

Big Data Software Engineer

Thiago Henrique Ramos da Mata +61 0413 065 180

e-mail: thiago.henrique.mata@gmail.com

Twitter: @thiagomata http://thiagomata.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/thiagomata/

https://github.com/thiagomata

https://stackoverflow.com/users/456164

Australian Resident - Visa Subclass 186

Summary

I started working in development as a software engineer in 2001. Since then, I have held many positions, including Front-end Developer, Database Administrator, Process Analyst, Developer Lead, Data Engineer, and Chief Technology Officer. These different perspectives have helped me better understand each area's particular needs and integrate them properly.

In recent years, I have specialised in Big Data, Cloud Computing and Machine Learning. I have worked with real-time systems, clusters, distributed systems, distributed storage, distributed search engines, functional programming, data streams, data processing pipelines and key-value and graph databases.

I am always searching for a balance between product demands and strategic needs by observing the complexity of implementation and the value proposition. I can combine my technical and academic framework, design and analysis aptitude, and communication skills to interact with the tech team, investors, clients, and executives, using prototyping, experimentation, data, and facts to aid decision-making.

I prefer a job where I can work and solve problems creatively. I seek opportunities to gain valuable skills while using my knowledge and capability to improve the company by developing and creating impactful, useful, reliable, elegant, clear, and thrifty products.

Education

Master's Degree, Biomedical Engineering

2011 - 2013

Universidade de Brasília - UnB with 4 publications.

Graduate Degree, Computer Science

2002 - 2008

Universidade de Brasília - UnB.

Experience

Senior Manager - Macquarie Bank

2024 - Preset

https://www.macquarie.com.au/

Sydney, Australia

Helping the Banking and Financial Services to provide fast and consistent responses related to the company's data products.

Git, Java, Kafka, CICD, Protobuf, GRPC, Google BigQuery, Apache Beam, Google DataFlow, Google Cloud Storage, Google Spanner, Google Cloud Functions, Google Pub/Sub, ElasticSearch, Dynatrace, CICD, Docker, Helm, and Kubernetes.

Senior Data Engineer - ROKT

2019 - 2024

https://rokt.com/

Sydney, Australia

I first worked on the Customer Data Platform, a real-time distributed system for organising, cleaning, validating, and enriching customer data. We then built the Identity System to group customer interactions for better behaviour analysis and the Attribution System to link interactions with advertiser conversion events, providing key campaign success metrics for machine learning models. On the Traffic Resilience team, I helped monitor and safeguard company traffic from Bots using real-time and offline analysis with statistical inference. Our evaluations, including rate limiting, local residency enforcement, and anomaly detection, run in Kubernetes Edge Clusters with Istio, Envoy Proxy, and gRPC-integrated services. Finally, I worked in the Anomaly Detection to monitor and detect unexpected changes in key metrics.

5 years and 5 months

Git, Java, Scala, Python, Go, Gremlin, Spark, Kafka, AWS SQS / SNS, AWS Redshift, AWS Neptune, AWS EC2, AWS EKS, AWS CloudFormation, AWS CloudWatch, AWS DynamoDB, Terraform, Elasticsearch, Redis, HBase, Grafana, Prometheus, DataDog, CICD, Buildkite, Docker, Helm, Kubernetes, Istio, Envoy and GRPC.

Senior Data Engineer - SLI Systems

2017 - 2019

https://www.sli-systems.com/

Christchurch, New Zealand

On the Analytics Team, we worked on adding new features to current products, creating new products with a high volume of data, prototyping, and online and offline testing new machine learning strategies using Cloud Computing. I translated the models from the Data Scientist to SQL and Spark Streaming. We also moved many company services from Apache Spark to Apache Beam, improving speed and cost.

1 year and 8 months

Git, Java, Python, Google BigQuery, Apache Beam, Google DataFlow, Google Cloud Storage, Google Spanner, Google Pub/Sub, ElasticSearch, CICD, Jenkins, Docker, Helm and Kubernetes.

Chief Technology Officer - Ideia Big Data

2014 - 2017

http://ideiabigdata.com

Brasília, Federal District, Brazil

I guided the company's strategy and vision in designing, modelling, and developing its product for research, microtargeting, communication, and statistics using publicly available demographic data, distributed systems, machine learning, and streaming on the cloud. We had to deal with Data Cleaning, Data Mining, Feature Extraction and Data Visualization. I also

3 years

improved the company development process and training policy, defined the career ladder, reported the company strategy and vision to investors, improved the observability and monitoring, evaluated product existing and new features with clients, measured their engagement and feedback, and optimised the cloud infrastructure for scalability and reliability while reducing the cost.

Git, PHP, Python, R, Scala, Node.JS, Postgres, Hadoop, Apache Spark, Redis, Memcached, Grafana, MongoDB, AWS EC2, AWS SQS / SNS, AWS S3, AWS Elastic Beanstalk, Cloudera, Elasticsearch, Vagrant, Docker, Angular, Laravel, Cordova, Bootstrap, JQuery, D3.js and PDF.js, Karma and Selenium.

Senior Programmer - Adjetiva

2014 - 2014

http://www.adjetiva.com.br/

Brasília, Federal District, Brazil

Here, I created the brand channel of Embratur, mobile applications for the World Cup Events, educational games, and the Fiat EcoDrive desktop application. We also developed the SAT-JF14, a mobile application winner of 3 Lion Cannes.

10 months

Java, Node.js, Angular 2, PHP, Laravel, Postgres, UML, Scrum, Cordova, Node Webkit and Phaser.

Co-Founder - OtimiCar

2013 - 2014 4 months

http://www.otimicar.com

Brasília, Federal District, Brazil

Otimicar is a hardware and app solution that converts any car into a smart car. In Otimicar, I worked with the first version of the server's specification and development. This server communicates with the hardware devices and some partners to sync the data about the cars and send recommendations for services and maintenance to the car owners. It also created reports to the partners about their customers and their products.

Git, Java, Node.js, Rest, Soap, MongoDB, UML, BPMN, Postgres, Google Web App and IoT.

Senior Coordinator - Grupo 954

2012 - 2013

http://www.grupo954.com

Brasília, Federal District, Brazil

The Grupo 954 provided clients with many data analyses, reports, and prediction models, including General Motors, one of Brazil's most significant car companies. I have modelled the internal business processes for estimating, specification and development for the company. Most of all, I worked developing web applications for the company's clients.

1 year and 6 months

Git, PHP, Oracle Database, MsSQL Server, Rest, UML, BPMN and Scrum.

Process Analyst - INEP

2009 - 2012

http://www.inep.gov.br/

Brasília, Federal District, Brazil

Here, I worked on many software systems with high availability, high data volumes, and a high number of concurrent users, around hundreds of millions, including the E-MEC, which is software for educational accreditation and quality assurance for all universities in the country, and Revalida, the National Examination for the Revalidation of Medical Diplomas Issued by Foreign Higher Education Institutions. I have also worked on the specification and development of many internal systems.

3 years and 1 month

PHP, Laravel, Zend, Java, JBoss Seam, Memcached, Oracle, Redis, BPMN and Scrum.

Teacher - Studio On-Line http://www.studioonline.com.br/ Brasília, Federal District, Brazil	2004 - 2010
Here, I taught PHP, MySQL, HTML, CSS and Javascript.	6 years
PHP, MySQL, HTML, CSS, Javascript	
Analyst and Web Developer - SECOM http://www.secom.gov.br/ Brasília, Federal District, Brazil	2008-2009
I worked with a Survey of Requirements, Modeling, Prototyping and Web Development there.	7 months
PHP, Oracle Database, Postgres, Zend and Javascript.	
Database Administrator - Bancoob http://www.bancoob.com.br/ Brasília, Federal District, Brazil	2007 - 2008
Here, I developed the system for portfolio credit transfers with a significant volume of financial transactions and ensured the accounting closing process. I used storage procedures, memory tables, transactions and bulk loading to deal with heavy data manipulation.	1 year and 2 months
Visual Basic, MsSQL Server, Java, Crystal Reports, and UML.	
Web Developer - Ministério da Educação http://www.mec.gov.br/ Brasília, Federal District, Brazil	2006 - 2007
We developed the System of Information and Supervision of Professional Education and Technology and the Integrated Planning, Budget and Finance System of Brazil's Ministry of Education. Those systems deal with a high volume of real-time and batch data and provide fast and dynamic reports.	1 year
SVN, PHP, Zend, Postgres, Javascript, and SVG.	
Senior Developer - AgênciaClick - Isobar https://www.isobar.com Brasília, Federal District, Brazil	2005 - 2006
Here, we developed the SISAC - System for Monitoring and Controlling Communication Actions to the Presidency of the Republic of Brazil, the BrazilTour site, and the RMA - Network of NGOs of the Atlantic Forest site.	1 year
PHP, Postgres, Oracle and Javascript.	
Developer - SAMU Brasília, Federal District, Brazil	2005 - 2005
The SAMU is a critical call centre software for emergency calls that connects the patient, ambulance driver, and medical team in one call. There, I worked as a front-end Software Developer to create the Internal System of Ambulance Request Manager.	6 months
Java, JSTL, CSS, Javascript, Struts and XUL.	

Developer - M.S.D. Brasília, Federal District, Brazil	2003 - 2004
Here, we developed some computer-based training using Adobe Authorware, Adobe Flash, Javascript and ToolBook.	11 months
Javascript, ToolBook, Adobe Authorware, Computer-Based Training and Adobe Flash.	

Knowledge and Skills

PHP	Javascript	Python	Node.js
Java	Scala	Go	Visual Basic
C#	Dafny	Haskell	R
Spark	Hadoop	Apache Beam	Kafka
MsSQL Server	Postgres	Oracle Database	MySQL
MongoDB	Redis	ElasticSearch	HBase
AWS EMR	AWS Athena	AWS DynamoDB	AWS Redshift
AWS Elastic Beanstalk	AWS Lambda	AWS SQS/SNS	AWS EC2
AWS CloudFormation	AWS CloudWatch	AWS CW Logs	AWS Neptune
Google Big Table	Google Spanner	Oracle Cloud	Terraform
Jenkins	BuildKite	Git	Bash
Kubernetes	Docker	Istio	Envoy

Languages

English 71/100 PTE Portuguese Native

Certifications

Parallel programming

2024

École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne

Programming with Google Go

2023

University of California, Irvine

Solutions Architect Associate Amazon Web Services	2022
<u>Functional Program Design in Scala</u> École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne	2021
Introduction to Graph Databases, Cypher, and Neo4j Pluralsight	2020
<u>Practical Machine Learning</u> Johns Hopkins University	2019
AWS Fundamentals: Going Cloud-Native Amazon Web Services	2019
Regression Models Johns Hopkins University	2019
<u>Deep Learning in Python Course</u> DataCamp	2017
<u>Leveraging Unstructured Data with Cloud Dataproc</u> Google Cloud Platform	2017
Big Data and Machine Learning Fundamentals Google Cloud Platform	2017
<u>Apache Spark 2.0 + Scala: DO Big Data Analytics & ML</u> Udemy - V2 Maestros	2017
Reproducible Research Johns Hopkins University	2017
<u>Functional Programming Principles in Scala</u> École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne	2016
<u>Exploratory Data Analysis</u> Johns Hopkins University	2016
<u>Getting and Cleaning Data</u> Johns Hopkins University	2016
<u>R Programming</u> Johns Hopkins University	2016
Introduction to Probability and Data Duke University	2016
The Data Scientist's Toolbox	2016

Johns Hopkins University

<u>Advanced Track of Introduction to Artificial Intelligence</u> **Stanford University**

2011

Publications

<u>Critérios de Usabilidade e Acessibilidade para Avaliação de</u> <u>Aplicações Educacionais 3D na Web</u> 2015

CBIE-LACLO 2015

<u>Definition of Computational Criteria to Evaluation of 3D Anatomical Web</u> <u>Manikins for Teaching in Health Science and for Medical Applications</u> 2013

PAHCE – Pan American Health Care Exchanges

Accessibility for Web 3D Anatomical Manikins

2013

SETI - First Symposium on Education and Inclusive Technology Regional Integrated University of High Uruguay and Missions

2012

<u>Definition of criteria for evaluating 3D anatomical manikins on the web</u> <u>for education in healthcare or medical applications</u>

Extensio: Electronic Journal of Extension

Honours & Awards

Honourable Mention in Ranking of the Best Published Articles - Conferência Latino-Americana de Objetos e Tecnologias de Aprendizagem - LACLO

2015

Gold Lion - 1º Place - Category Media, Entertainment and Leisure

2014

Cannes Lions - Campaign SAT-JF14. Record Collection Music Album - John Frusciante

Silver Lion - 2º Place - Category Use of Digital Platforms

2014

Cannes Lions - Campaign SAT-JF14. Record Collection Music Album - John Frusciante

Bronze Lion - 3° Place - Category New Product Launch

2014

Cannes Lions - Campaign SAT-JF14. Record Collection Music Album - John Frusciante